Guide to the William Miller Abrahams Papers, ca. 1945-1998
Department of Special Collections
- Series 3. Hellman Biography files
  The Hellman Biography Materials Series had little or no organization, the materials often mixed in with the Hellman-Hammett Trusts materials, but hand-labeled as research. The files are generally divided with Hellman material appearing first, and Hammett material following. The material consists of correspondence between Abrahams and other researchers, typescripts and photocopies of published and unpublished Hellman or Hammett works, photocopies of Hellman or Hammett correspondence, photocopied transcripts of interviews with Hellman, and photocopied newspaper and magazine articles regarding Hellman or Hammett. Please note that original Hellman correspondence may also appear within the Editorial Files Series in both subseries, to retain Abrahams' original order.
  - Correspondence: responses to request for information, 1984 (Box 71, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: from Rita Wade, Hellman's secretary, includes list of Hammett holdings at the University of Texas issued to Hellman in 1967, and photocopy of request by Abrahams to University of Teaxas for Hammett material, 1986 (Box 71, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: photocopied correspondence from the Little Brown Co. files, 1963-1969, Abrahams' correspondence regarding same, 1989 (Box 71, Folder 8)
  - Application for Hellman birth certificate, 1991, results of literature search at Tulane University (Box 71, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: tls from Jackson Breyer, includes tss of Hellman chronology and two interviews of Hellman by Richard Stern, 1958, and Fred Gardner, 1968 (Box 71, Folder 10)
  - Clark, Blair.: ts draft, recollection of personal relationship, 23 pp., with correspondence and photocopied reviews, 1989[?] (Box 71, Folder 11)
  - Hellman, Lillian, and Kronenberger, Louis. The dear queen: photocopied ts, 1935 (Box 71, Folder 12)
  - Hellman, Lillian. Candide: photocopied ts, obtained from University of Texas, 1986 (Box 72, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Hellman to the Steegmullers, 1969-1982, other correspondence to the Steegmullers regarding Hellman, 1984 (Box 72, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Abrahams-Hellman, 1979-1983 (Box 72, Folder 3)
  - Reference listing of correspondence held by University of Texas, Austin (Box 72, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Editorial correspondence and memorandums regarding Hellman's Pentimento, 1969-1973 (Box 72, Folder 5)
  - Photocopied ts: Small tales, 28 pp., found in 1983 correspondence file (Box 72, Folder 6)
  - Ts: Ruthie Murray, 51 pp, with tls, 1981, found in 1983 correspondence file (Box 72, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: request of Robert Newman to quote from Hellman-John Melby letters, photocopied pages of ts where quotes are used (Box 72, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: photocopied correspondence of Joseph Rauh, Lillian Hellman's attorney, 1950- 1986 [one of two] (Box 72, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: photocopied correspondence of Joseph Rauh, Lillian Hellman's attorney, 1950- 1986 [two of two] (Box 72, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Abrahams with publishing company, other researchers 1978-1993, Abrahams royalty statements, 1993-1994 (Box 72, Folder 11)
  - Chronological biographical files, pre1903-1953 (Box 72, Folder 12)
  - Chronological biographical files, 1954-1984 (Box 73, Folder 1)
  - Photocopied newspaper articles regarding Hellman, 1934-1952, photocopied interviews, etc., 1934-1981, received from Jackson R. Bryer, 1985 (Box 73, Folder 2)
  - Photocopied newspaper articles regarding Hellman, 1953-1981 (Box 73, Folder 3)
  - Sargent, Alvin. Two lives: photocopied ts of screenplay based upon Hellman-Hammett relationship, 1986 (Box 73, Folder 4)
  - Zwick, Edward M. Life in art: a study of Lillian Hellman and Watch on the Rhine: photocopied ts (Box 73, Folder 5)
  - Roughead, William. Closed doors, or the great Drumsheugh case: photocopied anthology article, basis for plot of Hellman's The children's hour, biographical notes on Hellman (Box 73, Folder 6)
  - Biographical information, list of quotations and sources [one of two] (Box 73, Folder 7)
  - Biographical information, list of quotations and sources [two of two] (Box 73, Folder 8)
  - Photocopied FBI files of Lillian Hellman, with legal correspondence, 1986 [one of five] (Box 74, Folder 1)
  - Photocopied FBI files of Lillian Hellman, 1986 [two of five] (Box 74, Folder 2)
  - Photocopied FBI files of Lillian Hellman, 1986 [three of five] (Box 74, Folder 3)
  - Photocopied FBI files of Lillian Hellman, 1986 [four of five] (Box 74, Folder 4)
  - Photocopied FBI files of Lillian Hellman, 1986 [five of five] (Box 74, Folder 5)
  - Photocopied FBI files of Lillian Hellman, released to Robert P. Newman, with correspondence, 1985-1986 [one of four] (Box 74, Folder 6)
  - Photocopied FBI files of Lillian Hellman, released to Robert P. Newman, with correspondence, 1985-1986 [two of four] (Box 74, Folder 7)
  - Photocopied FBI files of Lillian Hellman, released to Robert P. Newman, with correspondence, 1985-1986 [three of four] (Box 75, Folder 1)
  - Photocopied FBI files of Lillian Hellman, released to Robert P. Newman, with correspondence, 1985-1986 [four of four] (Box 75, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: photocopied letters, mostly Hammett to Hellman, some to daughters, 1943-1945 (Box 75, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: photocopies of letters to Hammett from Alfred Knopf, 1935, Hammett to Bill Glicken, 1944-1945 with research notes by Glockin, 1982,miscellaneous letters (Box 75, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: photocopied letters, mostly Hammet to Hellman, some to daughters, 1934-1950 (Box 75, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: photocopied letters and articles, mostly Hammett to daughters, some Hammett to Hellman, others, 1935-1949 (Box 75, Folder 6)
  - Transcript of interview with Hellman regarding Hammett's arrest and incarceration, ts, no date, interviewer unknown (Box 75, Folder 7)
  - Photocopied short stories by Hammett from anthologies [one of two] (Box 76, Folder 1)
  - Photocopied short stories by Hammett from anthologies [two of two] (Box 76, Folder 2)
  - Photocopied transcript of Hammett's testimony before the New York court, 1951; photocopies of journal articles regarding Senate appearance (Box 76, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: photocopied letters, memorandums regarding Hammett v. Warner Bros. (Box 76, Folder 4)
  - Photocopied FBI files of Dashiell Hammett [one of two] (Box 76, Folder 5)
  - Photocopied FBI files of Dashiell Hammett [two of two] (Box 76, Folder 6)
  - Dramatic contracts: photocopied, 1935-1941, includes The children's hour, The little foxes, and Watch on the Rhine [legal size] (Box 77, Folder 1)
  - Dramatic contracts: photocopied, 1944-1959, includes The searching wind, Monserrat, Another part of the forest, Candide [legal size] (Box 77, Folder 2)
  - Dramatic contracts: photocopied, 1959-1967, includes Candide[?], Toys in the attic, revivial of The little foxes [legal size] (Box 77, Folder 3)
  - Photocopied magazine article, unfinished first draft of Dashiell Hamett's Thin man, 1975 [legal size] (Box 77, Folder 4)
  - Dramatic contracts: photocopied, 1979-1982, includes revival of Watch on the Rhine, the little foxes etc., contract for Three [legal size] (Box 77, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: photocopied letters, Hammet to Hellman, 1943-1945, some to Hammett's daughters, 1943-1945, undated letter from Laura[?] [legal size] (Box 77, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: photocopied letters, Hammet to Hellman, 1943-1945, some to Hammett's daughters, 1942-1945 [one of two, legal size] (Box 77, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: photocopied letters, Hammet to Hellman, 1943-1945, some to Hammett's daughters, 1942-1945 [two of two, legal size] (Box 77, Folder 8)
  - Photocopied artistic contracts of Hammett, 1928-1929, photocopied issues of Army newspaper edited by Hammett, 1944, photocopied telegram regarding Hammett book sales, 1950, photocopied Army document regarding Hammett's service, 1974 [legal size] (Box 78, Folder 1)
  - Photocopied newspaper articles regarding Hammett's arrest and incarceration, 1950s [one of two, legal size] (Box 78, Folder 2)
  - Photocopied newspaper articles regarding Hammett's arrest and incarceration, some regarding the Thin Man radio series,1950s [two of two, legal size] (Box 78, Folder 3)
  - Photocopied newspaper articles regarding Hammett, 1950s [one of two, legal size] (Box 78, Folder 4)
  - Photocopied newspaper articles regarding Hammett, 1950s [two of two, legal size] (Box 78, Folder 5)
  - Photocopied articles and reviews regarding mostly Hammett's works, some Hellman [legal size] (Box 78, Folder 6)
  - Photocopied hospital records of Dashiell Hamett, 1955-1961 (Box 79, Folder 1)
  - Benstock, Bernard. Love, hate, and pity, the Lillian Hellman--Dashiell Hammett affair: photocopied ts, chapters 1-4 (Box 79, Folder 2)
  - Benstock, Bernard. Love, hate, and pity, the Lillian Hellman--Dashiell Hammett affair: photocopied ts, chapters 5-8 (Box 79, Folder 3)
  - Benstock, Bernard. Love, hate, and pity, the Lillian Hellman--Dashiell Hammett affair: photocopied ts, chapters 9-12 (Box 79, Folder 4)
  - Photocopied ts: The case of Dashiell Hammett, teleplay, author unknown (Box 79, Folder 5)
  - Photocopied ts of short stories written by Hammett while living in San Francisco, obtained from the University of Texas (Box 79, Folder 6)
  - Thompson, George, J. Red harvest, the pragmatic and moral dilemma: photocopied critical essay (Box 79, Folder 6)
  - Photocopied ts of short stories written by Hammett while living in San Francisco, obtained from the University of Texas [second copy] (Box 80, Folder 1)
  - Photocopied newspaper and magazine articles regarding Hellman (Box 80, Folder 2)
  - Hellman, Lillian. I call her momma now: computer print out of story appearing in the American Spectator, September, 1933 (Box 80, Folder 3)
  - Draft of Abrahams' introduction to biography, ts, edited and incomplete (Box 80, Folder 4)
  - Photocopied book reviews written by Hellman, 1927-1929, photocopied newspaper article regarding Hellman's play, Days to come, 1936 (Box 80, Folder 5)
  - Publicity jacket for Herbert Mitgang's Dangerous dossiers: exposing the secret war against America's greatest authors (Box 80, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous material: unpublished photograph of Hellman, photocopied article regarding Abrahams' status as official biographer, some editorial material (Box 80, Folder 7)
  - Wright, William. Lillian Hellman:photocopied ts, chapters 1-10 (Box 80, Folder 8)
  - Wright, William. Lillian Hellman:photocopied ts, chapters 11-21 (Box 80, Folder 9)
  - Wright, William. Lillian Hellman:photocopied ts, chapters 22-31, epilogue (Box 80, Folder 10)
  - Photocopied news articles regarding Hammett, 1950s (Box 81, Folder 2)
  - Photocopied newspaper articles, related to Hammett's early career as a detective (Box 81, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: photocopied legal correspondence and documents regarding Hammett v. Warner Bros. (Box 81, Folder 4)
  - Photocopied contract for The thin man, with MGM, 1934 (Box 81, Folder 5)
  - Photocopied legal petition by literary trustees, Hellman's will, and related correspondence (Box 81, Folder 6)
  - The official Lillian Hellman biography address book (Box 82, Folder 1)
- Series 4. Personal papers
  The Personal Series contains some personal and business correspondence regarding the published works of Abrahams and his collaborative efforts with Peter Stansky, typescript of an unpublished poem and novel, legal papers, and personal effects.
  - Contracts: Interval in Carolina, 1945, 1946, By the beautiful sea, 1947, Children of Capricorn, 1961 (Box 82, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: professional and personal, regarding Abrahams' novel, Children of Capricorn, 1960-1964 (Box 82, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: photocopied letters and contract regarding paperback re-issue of The imperial waltz, 1979-1980 (Box 82, Folder 4)
  - Abrahams, William, and Kalstone, David. The craft of the story: ts prospectus, photocopy of same (Box 82, Folder 5)
  - Abrahams, William, and Stansky, Peter. Hunting the unicorn: George Orwell in the 1930s: ts, incomplete draft of first and second chapters (Box 82, Folder 6)
  - Abrahams, William. Book reviews and journal articles, ts, photocopied ts, and photocopied newspaper articles, 1975-1989 (Box 82, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: professional and personal regarding Abrahams-Stanky's Journey to the frontier, 1965-1969 (Box 82, Folder 8)
  - Photocopied newspaper and magazine aricles regarding Abrahams, photocopied reviews of Abrahams-Stansky's Journey to the frontier, miscellaneous phtocopied articles (Box 82, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Mrs. Giles Whiting foundation, solicitation of nominees for award, 1997, Joseph Henry Jackson and James D. Phelan awards, brochure and rules for judgement, 1988 (Box 82, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Photocopied newspaper and magazine aricles regarding Abrahams, photocopied reviews of Abrahams-Stansky's Journey to the frontier, miscellaneous phtocopied articles (Box 82, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: John Brinnan, 1976-1980 (Box 82, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: miscellaneous personal letters, two from Jessica Mitford, three addressed to or from Peter Stansky, 1976-1992 (Box 82, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Charitable donations, 1975 (Box 82, Folder 13)
  - Wood, Charles T. In memoriam, Charles Holt Taylor: photocopied ts (Box 82, Folder 14)
  - Brochure for Stanford writing course, with annotated biography of Abrahams, 1983 (Box 82, Folder 15)
  - Receipts, business cards etc., found in correspondence file, 1972, wedding invitation, 1976 (Box 82, Folder 17)
  - Legal documnets regarding real property, Palo Alto, Pajaro Dunes, 1976 (Box 82, Folder 18)
  - Royalty statements, 1974-1975 (Box 82, Folder 19)
  - Legal documents regarding the estate of Louis Abrahams, 1967, and Fanny Landers, 1967 (Box 82, Folder 20)
  - List of passengers, T.S.S. Nieuw Amsterdam, 9/8/53, Mr. P. Stansky listed in tourist class, unidentified photographs, found in correspondence file, 1972 (Box 82, Folder 21)
  - Abrahams, William. Now and zen: ts of poem, found in correspondence file, 1972 (Box 82, Folder 22)
  - Abrahams, William. The black sheep: unpublished novel, ts, pp 1-175 (Box 83, Folder 1)
  - Abrahams, William. The black sheep: unpublished novel, ts, pp 176-368 (Box 83, Folder 2)
  - Abrahams, William. The black sheep: unpublished novel, ts, pp 369-571 (Box 83, Folder 3)